<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true narrative (in a letter written to Col. B.R. an Honorable Member of Parliament:) of the apprehension of the grand traytor, Thomas Scot: wherein is shewn, his arrtifice [sic] and subtil endeavours to shun his apprehension, and wherein he hath judged himself not worthy of any mercy for that detestable murder of His late Majesty of ever blessed memory. Published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1046_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208020</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867026</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867026</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86281)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 155:E1046[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true narrative (in a letter written to Col. B.R. an Honorable Member of Parliament:) of the apprehension of the grand traytor, Thomas Scot: wherein is shewn, his arrtifice [sic] and subtil endeavours to shun his apprehension, and wherein he hath judged himself not worthy of any mercy for that detestable murder of His late Majesty of ever blessed memory. Published by authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Matthew Inman, and are to be sold by James Magnes in Russel Street in Covent Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: C.H.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 4".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scott, Thomas, d. 1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Treason --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Regicides --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE NARRATIVE (IN A LETTER Written to Col. <hi>B. R.</hi> and Honorable Member OF PARLIAMENT:) OF THE APPREHENSION Of the Grand TRAYTOR, Thomas Scot: <hi>Wherein is ſhewn,</hi> His Arrtifice and ſubtil Endeavours to ſhun his Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and wherein he hath judged himſelf not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of any Mercy for that deteſtable Murder of His late Majeſty of everbleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by AUTHORITY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Inman,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>James Magnes</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel Street</hi> in <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119316:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the ever honorable Col.</hi> B. R. <hi>an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Member of the Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Diſcourſe we held at our laſt interview, wherein by your words I diſcovered a ſenſe of ſome honourable Member of the Houſe of Commons, ſeeming to mittigate the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty due to the guilt of that impious Villain <hi>SCOT,</hi> by his pretence of rendring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his Majeſties Reſident in <hi>Brabant,</hi> according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Proclamation made to that effect, hath obliged me to make diligent ſearch after Capt. <hi>Comb,</hi> whom I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by ſeveral perſons of Honour, to have been the firſt man that apprehended him and who coming for <hi>England</hi> to inform his Majeſty thereof, received a moſt gracious reward and thanks for his ſervice therein: And the relation of the whole buſineſs which I here ſent you, I have both his Faith and Honour not to exceed in the leaſt circumſtance, the truth of the paſſage thereof, and the good qualities <hi>I</hi> find in him, eſpecially his marvellous zeal to his Majeſties ſervice, ſo perfectly well anſwering the Character. I had before recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of him, gave me confidence enough to believe that the publiſhing of this Relation to the view of all, might ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what conduce to the diſ-abuſing of that promptitude which in ſome perſons might have raiſed a propenſion againſt the common cry for Juſtice, in vindication of God's glory, his Majeſties Honour, and the ſatisfaction of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, upon one of the bloodieſt Monſters that nature hath produced in many ages.</p>
            <p>Upon the fifth of <hi>Iune</hi> laſt paſt, according to the calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119316:2"/>
of thoſe Countreys, the ſaid <hi>Scot</hi> was diſcovered by an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Knight, called Sir <hi>William Perſal</hi> (walking in the Park at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> to take the evening air, and as it is to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that that Hell which he carryed within him, as never wanting attendant to ſuch notorious conſciouſneſs) was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways active to make him circumſpect; whom he met, he no ſooner perceived Sir <hi>Williams</hi> eye to be fixed upon him, but to divert his acquaintance (which could not but be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom) he turned himſelf to gaze upon the Trees; an action better ſuiting to confirm a man, who (by the inconveniences he had received in the knowledge he had of him in <hi>England)</hi> knew him but too well, then to diſtract the notice he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of him in an other Countrey, where he had no power to harm him: Sir <hi>William</hi> very skilfully accepted this feint; but with a reſolution to anſwer it with another which might wound <hi>Scot</hi> to the heart; and therefore paſſing on his way without any ſtop or ſeeming ſurprize, ſo ſoon as he perceived <hi>Scot</hi> to haſten towards the Park Gate, he accoſted a certain <hi>Dutch</hi> man, and gave him a piece of money to dog that man (pointing at him) to his lodging, with promiſe of as much more to come and inform him of it at his lodging: This was readily undertaken, and as effectually performed. He having received this Light from the <hi>Dutch</hi> man, imparted this his diſcovery to ſome Officers of his Majeſties Regiment of Guards, (at that time, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſiding in <hi>Brabant)</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the difficulty that might ariſe in ſo important an undertaking, thought meet to communicate it to Capt. <hi>Comb,</hi> (as a man by his long ſervice in that Countrey, in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to be better verſed in what Method was moſt fit to be taken for the carrying on of a deſign which promiſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of difficulty to them themſelves:) This was done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; and upon their conſult with him, their firſt reſolution was, with all poſſible skill that very night to endeavor to pry into his hants, and the time of his arrival thither, whereof they found means to be ſatisfied from the Maid of the Houſe where he lodged; but in ſuch ſort as ſhe could not gather any the leaſt ſign of deſign againſt him. His arrival unto that place was about ſix dayes before all the viſits he made to <hi>Don Allon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119316:3"/>
               <hi>de Cardenas,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador, who had ſo long reſided here in <hi>England,</hi> and all the Company he kept, was one <hi>White</hi> a ſervant to the ſaid Embaſſador, and his ſworn ſpye into all places, eſpecially into <hi>England,</hi> having immediately before been employed by him to the backing of <hi>Lamberts</hi> traiterous deſign in his laſt attempt, which to his eternal confuſion, and the general joy of all Chriſtendom, was ſo ſuccesfully and timely cruſht. <hi>Scot</hi> was at that inſtant upon a viſit to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous Embaſſador, and was ſeen by Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentleman, to come forth of his houſe at eleven of the Clock that night, and to go into his own lodging, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by the ſaid <hi>White.</hi> The buſineſs being thus far carryed on without any noiſe, before the opening of the Gates next morning, ſuch order was taken by placing ſecret Centinels in every corner of the ſtreet, that <hi>Scot</hi> was in a net, without dreaming of his misfortune, while Capt. <hi>Comb,</hi> by reaſon of what they all might juſtly apprehend poſſibly to occur in an illegal proceeding, made his Addreſſes to the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>He bears the ſame Authority there, as the Recorder doth in</hi> London.</note> 
               <hi>Aman</hi> of <hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els;</hi> who being a Gentleman that upon all occaſions had te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified ſufficiently his zeal unto his Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> his ſervice when he reſided in thoſe parts, perſwaded him hee might hope from him, if no aſſiſtance, yet ſo much conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance as might be neceſſary in that caſe, to avoid any popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar tumult, (the onely obſtruction to be feared) for the ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the deſign; the whole matter being opened to the <hi>Aman,</hi> he anſwered, that he had always been, and was ſtill moſt ready, and ambitions of any ſervice wherein he might be thought worthy to employ his endeavours for the ſatisfaction of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britany;</hi> but that he might be called to a ſure account, if he did him any, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of his Maſters Authority, by whoſe onely power he was to act, and by whoſe rules, and no others, they were all to live; that although from his heart he did abhor, and would gladly ſee brought to condigne puniſhment all thoſe that combined, and more eſpecially thoſe that acted his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Englands</hi> deſtruction: Yet he knew not how this Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive, who was accuſed to be one, ſhould become reſponſible in that Countrey for crimes he committed in another. And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119316:3"/>
upon Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> his anſwer, that he deſired him not at all to act therein, but that his connivance onely was that he peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for, which will be ſo grateful, and ſo well received (ſaid he) by the King, my Maſter, that in all occaſions where his acknowledgement might be expected, you ſhall never ſail to find a return. He replied, that that would yet prove more irregular; for <hi>I</hi> had rather (ſaid he) anſwer an error com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, where my Authority was miſtaken, then the ſuffering of another, which hath no pretence in my Juriſdiction, and in my view to execute: what immediately is contingent to my charge; and that except there were command from the higher Powers, (which neither was likely, there being no Embaſſador of the King of <hi>England's,</hi> as yet to move the Court in ſuch a buſineſs, with that credit and skill that might well be thought ſuiting to the expedition requiſite thereunto: He knew no way of proceeding, but what was too hazardous either to undertake, or to connive at, and therefore ſeemed very much troubled by being neceſſitated to the denial he gave him: Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> after a little pauſe, with much earneſtneſs repreſented, that he could never like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect a more juſt occaſion to teſtifie his deſire of gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> then that which ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned his Honour, that when there were difficulties which himſelf was likewiſe ſenſible of, that his endeavours in that act would bear proportion unto them, by the ſence his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would entertain of the ſervice done, and that he refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the conduct thereof unto his prudence, which he doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not (if well apply'd) would be able to diſſipate whatſoever-impediments ſeemed moſt obvious; adding, That he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved little danger in ſecuring this Monſter for a time, who at worſt might he releaſt if Higher Powers ſhould interpoſe in his favor. But when he received his final Anſwer, that the firſt motion in ſuch a caſe muſt be from thoſe Higher Powers, and that himſelf as an inferior Magiſtrate, durſt not attempt to reſtrain any man ſuſpected of falſeneſs to a forreign Prince, to the Prejudice of thoſe, with more vehemency then before, he reſolutely told him, That himſelf was the laſt to be valued of many Gentlemen now preſent in town,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119316:4"/>
who were reſolved rather to run the hazard of racks and Gibbets, then to ſuffer the Murderer of their Prince to be un-interrupted in a Countrey where they had any being; and that the ſame ſence which bore the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation with the hazard of their Lives and Fortunes to diſ-involve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs from the fetres which held their King and Countrey in ſlavery, would furniſh them with ſuch Reſolutions againſt this Traytor, that perhaps might lay an unhappy ground of a fatal miſ-underſtanding (which God forbid) between the two Crowns, there wanting not ſpirits on both ſides too prone to ſuch diſtempers, as might endanger the happineſs to be hoped for in their mutual friendſhip; and therefore ſince nothing (ſaid he) is of conſideration in your Office, but the ſervice of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> (your Maſter) for the prevention of ſuch inconveniences which might poſſibly turn to his diſſervice, give me onely under your hand a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to ſeize him, and ſecure him in ſome of the Town-Priſons till further Order, and I engage my ſelf unto you, there ſhall be no outrage offered him. The <hi>Aman</hi> revolving in his thoughts, that what was inferred bore ſhew enough not to be thought impoſſible; and making a ſhort reflection upon what happened at the <hi>Hague</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and at <hi>Madrid</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> upon the perſons ſent thither by that treacherous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, (their Maſter) to avoid what inconveniency might ariſe there by the like forces diſorder, conſented to give him this enſuing Licenſe, the Original whereof I have yet in my hands, and which my ſelf tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> word for word.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>The Copy of the Order for the ſeizing of <hi>SCOT.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>I Under-written give leave unto Capt.<hi> Comb, </hi>belonging to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of his Majeſty of Great<hi> Britany, </hi>to apprehend for ſome Reaſons he hath declared unto me, a certain Engliſh man in this Town, and to ſend him to what priſon he ſhall think meet; commanding the Maſters of the<hi> Urunt </hi>and<hi> Steenport </hi>to receive the ſaid Engliſh man into their priſon reſpectively, when by the ſaid Capt.<hi> Comb </hi>they ſhall be required ſo to do.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Dated at<hi> Bruxels</hi> 
                              <date>this ſixth of<hi> June, 1660.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Signed,</hi> George de Brimeen.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <trailer>Amen de Bryard.</trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119316:4"/>
Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> being well ſatisfied with the permiſſion he had thus wreſted from the <hi>Aman,</hi> haſted to his friends; but upon his communicating unto them the fruits of his nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation he found ſome of them a little diſtracted in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, having been by ſome there perſwaded, and were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready bent to proceed after another manner, telling Cap. <hi>Comb</hi> it was but juſt to defer the apprehenſion of this man til they knew his Majeſties pleaſure, which they were already conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering hovv to procure; he knovving them all to be ſuch who were as jealous of his Majeſties Honor as any men living, was not a little amaz'd at this their change, but remembring that this Imp of Hell might as well learn Witchcraft, as Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from his infernal Maſter; he onely told them, that he was now more concern'd then any, and that having remov'd the main obſtacle, he now was not to fear leſſer ones; &amp; therefore leaving them all a little abruptly, he invited one Major <hi>Shaw,</hi> a very ancient man, and no leſs zealous towards his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſervice to accompany him, and ſo upon pretence of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with a Gentleman who lodged in the ſame houſe where <hi>Scot</hi> did, leaving two Souldiers in the ſtreet, he entered with the ſaid Sergeant Major, and found <hi>Scot</hi> at din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: The Gentleman to whom he excuſed his boldneſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo ſlender an acquaintance; after he had cauſed them both to fit, told him he was to take notice of that Gentleman (which was <hi>Scot,</hi> a Countrey-man (ſaid he) of yours) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being right over againſt him at the Table, he gave him him a Salute, telling him he was glad to ſee any of his Countrey, <hi>Scot</hi> ſeemed little taken with the Diſcovery, and anſwered little or nothing: But the Captain who had more buſineſs with him then he was yet ſenſible of, was willing to hear him ſpeak a little plainer; and that he might, began to congratulate this our happy late deliverance, which would (ſaid he) make us all friends now, whereas for theſe 19 years paſt we have all groaned under ſuch inteſtine quarrels as have raiſed defiances betwixt the neareſt relations. <hi>Scot</hi> cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered, <hi>It is ſo.</hi> He asked him, Whether there was any <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> defeat.</note> preparation for his Majeſties reception before his coming o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? To which <hi>Scot</hi> anſwered, <hi>That he had been * twenty dayes</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119316:5"/>
               <hi>out of England; but that there was ſpeech before his departure of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring</hi> White-Hall, <hi>St.</hi> James, <hi>and</hi> Hampton-Court. Captain <hi>Comb</hi> anſwered, that thoſe indeed were very famous Houſes, but that they had been prophaned by moſt vile actions, and ſuch, that were it his caſe, as it was the Kings, he knew not whether he ſhould ever delight to live in them; becauſe (ſaid he) in the one they kept his Royal Father Priſoner, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gate of the other (to the aſtoniſhment and horror of the whole world) ſo barbarouſly butchered him. To which <hi>Scot</hi> remained ſilent. What courſe (ſaid Capt. <hi>Comb)</hi> did thoſe Villains omit, better ſuiting to have wrought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair in his late Majeſty, then what they took, in caſe his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſoul had not been fortified with Divine Grace. Surely (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he) their malice aimed at his eternal, as well as his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral deſtruction, whereunto he received no anſwer: But now urged he further upon this turn of the Kings Fortune: Do any of thoſe inſulting Wretches, falling into his Friends hands, deſerve any favor? Whereat <hi>Scot</hi> began to look unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, but replyed not, till having itterated the ſame three times, he peremptorily asked him the <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d.</hi>
               </hi> time, What his ſence was of them? And then <hi>Scot</hi> anſwered, <hi>Truly they deſerve none.</hi> Truly then (replied Capt. <hi>Comb)</hi> your ſelf muſt expect no <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Here</hi> Scot <hi>judgeth himſelf.</hi>
               </note> greater a meaſure; for you are accuſed by a man of Honour within this City, to be one who hath been as prodigal of that deteſtable malice that wrought the ruin of his Royal Perſon, and the whole Kingdome, as any in <hi>England:</hi> I have here, (ſaid he) an Order to ſeize you, and there is a Guard in the ſtreet; but becauſe my Opinion of the man of this Houſe, induces me to believe, that had he known you, he would never have ſuffered your breath within his doors for fear of a contagion. I contented my ſelf to come in onely accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by this ſole Gentleman; but you are my Priſoner, ſit ſtil and make no diſturbance. <hi>Scot</hi> ſo ſoon as he could recal his Reaſon, which was leaving him to ſhift for himſelf, asked who he was there taken for, and was anſwered, For oue <hi>Scot,</hi> of the number of thoſe imparaleld Rebels who qualified themſelves with the title of being Judges to their natural Prince. Oh Sir, (anſwered he) upon my word you are abuſed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119316:5"/>
upon my word you are; my Name is not ſo, neither do I know the man: And being asked his Name, he ſaid his Name was <hi>Alliſon,</hi> his Countrey was <hi>Eſſex,</hi> born he was at a place called <hi>Durmow,</hi> and his Profeſſion a Merchant; and that by reaſon of ſhipwracks, and ſome other croſſes that he had ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained, he was now become ſo far ſhort of his wont, that he was conſtrained to keep himſelf cloſe; which he judged the onely thing that had there brought him into ſuſpition; but he thankt God he came not into thoſe parts without a Paſs, which he was ready to produce: The paſſe being demanded, was produced accordingly, and indeed was ſigned by the Marqueſs of <hi>Caracena,</hi> (Capt. Gen. of thoſe Countreys) for <hi>Alliſon</hi> a Merchant freely to have egreſs and regreſs in, and out of the Ports and Cities of that Juriſdiction, without any let or diſturbance; but he was like to fal into a ſecond trance <note place="margin">For the ſpace of ſix Months.</note> when Mr. <hi>Comb</hi> told him that his Paſs being ſurrepted upon a falſe Name from the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Miniſters, would onely by the forfeitures he had incurred in the ſurreption of it, be uſeful to furniſh him with a Gallows there, if he failed of one in <hi>England;</hi> but howſoever he ſtrugled out this Anſwer; <hi>Well Sir, proceed legally, and I fear not to clear my ſelf.</hi> To which was returned, I ſhall indeed; I will not do by you as you did by your Maſter: Sir <hi>William Perſal</hi> is the man who juſtifies you to be <hi>Scot,</hi> and will preſently be here with you face to face. During this debate, <hi>Scot</hi> having his Quarter in the <hi>Jews</hi> Street, as near to <hi>Don Allonſo,</hi> as the conveniency of his <note place="margin">Scot <hi>lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the</hi> Iews <hi>ſtreet near to Don</hi> Allonſo, <hi>a ſine Emb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> cloſe viſits to him, did require. Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> is of opinion, that his man perceiving his Maſters reſtraint, ran over to give information to the ſaid <hi>Don Allonſo</hi> thereof; for imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately came the foreſaid <hi>White</hi> from him in vindication of <hi>Scot,</hi> deeply proteſting him not to be the man: But when he ſaw that no perſwaſion was of uſe, and that nothing but the hand of Authority would ever be able to remove what was ſo well founded; he betook himſelf to entreaties that he <note place="margin">That upon his Maſters and his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>role for his forth-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> might not be ſtirred from his lodging. Whereunto Captain <hi>Comb</hi> (well knowing the Embaſſador's power there.) anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That ſince his Excellency thought the Priſoner worthy his conſideration; he would that night leave him in his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119316:6"/>
but that he hoped he would be no wayes offended with him if he took care of his ſecurity: And thereupon leaving the Centinels with ſuch inſtructions as were fitting, the man of the Houſe likewiſe engaging that the Priſoner ſhould not ſtir, he went in ſearch of Sir <hi>William Perſal,</hi> whoſe task was a very hard one indeed, to perſwade a Traytor to know himſelf; at his coming thither, though his Diſcourſe was conſtant and conſonant to what he firſt depoſed, remembring <hi>Scot</hi> of Particulars, as his committing him at ſuch a time, from ſuch a place, after he had examined him upon ſuch and ſuch points, <hi>Scot</hi> would in no wiſe be <hi>Scot,</hi> but ſtill a broken Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, whoſe onely crime was mis-fortune; and therefore <hi>Combs</hi> troubled himſelf with nothing more that night, then to take care of what he had promiſed the Embaſſador, and not exaſperate him by ſeeming over-hot in the proſecuting what was ſo little pleaſing to him; but on the morrow ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the morning, he coming accompanied by ſome Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his Maieſties Regiment of Guard, now reſolved to ſend <hi>Scot</hi> to a place where leſs care and trouble might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible for him; he found this following Letter written by the Mediation of the Embaſſador, from the <hi>Aman</hi> of <hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> unto him in revocation of the permiſſion and order he had already granted him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To Capt. <hi>Combs,</hi> belonging to the Regiment of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Great Britany. Bruxels</hi> this <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1660.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I Underſtand that the man which you deſire to ſtop in this Town, came into thoſe parts with a Paſſe from his Excellency; ſo that he is not arreſtable. I am likewiſe credibly informed, that the ſaid perſon is not he whom you take him to be, wherein you have been abuſed. Hereupon I find my ſelf obliged to revogue the Permiſſion I gave you to ſeize him in this Town, for the Reaſons you were pleaſed to declare unto me, which</hi> I <hi>do hereby revogue, together with the Order I gave you for the Maſters of the Urunt and Steenport: I pray be pleaſed to regulate your ſelf accordingly: otherwiſe you will</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119316:6"/>
               <hi>offend his Excellency, and incur his indignation. Kiſſing your hands, I remain,</hi> Sir, <hi>your humble ſervant,</hi> George de Brimen.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Traytors heart began to bloom, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as indeed he had reaſon) that <hi>Don Allonſo</hi>'s patronage, the revocation of the Order for his arreſt, together with <hi>Whites</hi> activity, was ſubject enough for him to receive ſome impreſsion of comfort, he began to feaſt himſelfe at the ſurprize of his honeſt Enemy, finding ſo powerful a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in an abominable friend. <hi>Comb</hi> notwithſtanding would not yet releaſe him; revolving with himſelf that, by how much the more he ſtrugled in the difficulty; if the worſt happened, he might with the more facility give an account thereof, as well in order to his Maſters ſatisfaction, as in its due time, to the accuſing of ſuch who were the authors of ſo great a neglect to his greatneſs, in favour of his mortal e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. He therefore left thoſe Gentlemen at the houſe where <hi>Scot</hi> lay, and went himſelf to ſpeak with the <hi>Aman,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs him (if poſsible) of that Goblin that (as he thought) frighted him from owning a good work; encountring with him upon the way to his houſe, the <hi>Aman</hi> after a civil ſalute, (readily throwing down the Boot of his Coach, and inviting Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> in, asked him whether he had the Letter he ſent him? He anſwered him, Yes, and am very ſorry to ſee you repenting of a good action. The <hi>Aman</hi> anſwered, Sir, you are abuſed; the Protection that this man hath here, could never anſvver the notorious guilt of ſuch horrid crimes as you mark him with; for I cannot believe that ſo great a Stateſman, ſo eminent a perſon, &amp; ſo pious a Chriſtian as he, from whom I have my diſcharge, is univerſally judged to be, ſhould ever be brought ſo much to derogate from himſelf, as in his boſom to ſhrowd a man who had himſelf ſo far extm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht the Laws of Charity; that for him to hope any prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from a man of honor, ſeemed a new crime: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (Sir, added he) as it is an over-ſight in you, it would be a notable fault in me to believe it; and you cannot do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then in conſideration of the fright and diſgrace you have brought the Gentleman to, who by the Protection he hath,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119316:7"/>
appears to be an innocent man, to repair what hath raſhly been done to his prejudice, by ſome civil acknowledgement, which is no more (ſaid he) then I believe your own inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will adviſe you to: To this was oppoſed the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this mans leaving <hi>England</hi> in this conjuncture of time, his cloſe lurking in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> with his hants onely to ſuch as maugre their ſhews of piety and ſplendid greatneſs, were for many years (not without ſufficient ground) highly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected of the greateſt diſſervice to the King of <hi>England,</hi> but above all, the honor and integrity of Sir <hi>William Perſal,</hi> who (ſaid Capt. <hi>Comb)</hi> if you will pleaſe to make a viſit to any <hi>Engliſh</hi> in town, you will find not to be a man falſely to brand an innocent neighbor with ſuch ſcandalous and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous imputations. The <hi>Aman</hi> coldly replyed, That having already his diſcharge from one whoſe greatneſs was too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable to ſuffer him to conteſt with, he was not minded to take any further trouble upon himſelf, nor to put any more upon him. Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> then ſeeing him balk in good earneſt, entreated him, that for the prevention of ſuch diſorders that he had hinted to him at his firſt viſit, as well as for his own honor, he would be pleaſed to ſuffer the Guards to continue till himſelf went to <hi>Trerence,</hi> where the Marqueſs of <hi>Carace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> who was Governor of thoſe Provinces, and to whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority the ſtate of the buſineſs did more immediately ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain, was at that time by reaſon of the death of one of his children, retired; which the <hi>Aman</hi> moſt willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, telling him, That he was very glad he had thought upon it; and that he would in this, ſtretch his Authority to its utmoſt bounds, and to ſhew how much he was a ſervant to the King of <hi>Great Britany,</hi> do in that more then he was wel able to juſtifie. Thanks being duely returned, Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> after he had taken order for ſecuring him afreſh, haſtened to the Marqueſs of <hi>Caracena,</hi> where he found <hi>White</hi> walking in the Court-Hall with ſome <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentlemen, expecting the time of audience. <hi>White</hi> ſeeming ſomewhat ſurprized at his arrival thither, began to court him to a conference; but he (openly) in preſence of Sergeant Major <hi>Geraldin,</hi> and two more <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentlemen, told him, that being now upon a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119316:7"/>
ſo important to his Majeſties ſervice, he ſhould have care enough not to blemiſh himſelf by entertaining any propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals from one whom the King had already an ill mark upon; he told him further, that he might upon his Maſters ſcore to which effect he well knew he was ſent thither) purſue the Liberty of the moſt abominable Traytor, but that he ſhould have a care not to do it with any diſ-reſpect to himſelf, who came thither for his Maj. vindication, &amp; that therefore he was (notwithſtanding his Maſters great credit, and his own ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſhip) to ſuffer him in time of audience, to ſpeak both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after him, or to indure the worſt affront that poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he could invent to caſt upon him in the face of the Court. <hi>White</hi> anſwered, That he would in no wiſe interrupt him in it, but that he might do well not to be ſo far tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported. The time being come, Capt. <hi>Comb</hi> preſt for audience in the firſt place; and having performed his reſpects to the Marqueſs, he told him that he came to petition his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the behalf of all the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Subjects in thoſe parts, in a matter which he doubted not would by himſelf be judged well beſeeming their Allegiance, &amp; a fit ſubject for his favor. But when he had made a ſhort Narrative of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Marqueſs ſeemed ſo aſtoniſht, that he was ſeen by way of admiration to croſs himſelf two or three times cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, <hi>Is it poſſible! Such a man at Bruxels!</hi> Yes Sir, (anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Capt. <hi>Comb)</hi> and more, he hath your Excellency's Paſs: Whereat the Marqueſs haſtily ſtepping back, asked; <hi>How ſo?</hi> It is (Sir) ſaid he, upon a falſe Name, procured for him by a mighty man within your Excellencies Juriſdiction, who hath ſince which ſeizing him at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> endeavored his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe might and main, &amp; now hath ſent to protect him with your Excellency: Who (ſaid the Marqueſs) ſhould protect ſuch a man? There (Sir, ſaid he) is his Inſtrument, (point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>White)</hi> that doth it; It is <hi>Don Allonſo de Cardenas:</hi> But I have reaſon to hope leſs hard meaſure from your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, then to be diſcountenanced in my endeavours, to nearly relating to my Maſters ſervice: This Traytors Liberty is (ſaid he) repugnant to the ſpirits of all ſuch that wiſh his Majeſty well, that had I not applyed much induſtry, which I did rather for fear of diſpleaſing your Excellency, then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119316:8"/>
for any ſafety I intended him, his caſe had (ſince <hi>Don Allon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo's</hi> oppoſing his Arreſt) been already concluded; but I am moſt glad that I have found time to expect his ſentence from your Excellency, which I doubt not (if favourable to his Majeſty, his Fortune being not anſwerable to his inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) will be bountifully repaid, humbly beſeeching him to take it into his ſerious conſideration. The Marqueſs anſwered, That for his part he never intended either Paſs on Protection to ſuch a man, that if he had by ſurprize obtained one in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans Name, he ſhould be very much obliged to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in thoſe parts, that every one of them would have the ſame ſence of it as himſelf; &amp; aſſured him, that he would take ſuch courſe therein, that his Majeſtey of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſhould have a good account thereof, and that he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately think of it. <hi>Mr. Comb</hi> according to his firſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſpeak laſt, was well contented to break off here, as well knowing that <hi>White</hi> muſt have audience, having bin ſent from the Embaſſador, out of conſideration to whom, the Marqueſs might chance to totter into ſome remiſsneſs, which the more oppoſed, would in all likelyhood prove the leſs va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, to give way to others, withdrew himſelf a little.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Barbanſon,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Walfeuſe,</hi> and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Baſcourt,</hi> having imperfectly taken notice of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with the Marqueſs, invited him ſo ſoon as he was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, to give them a more perfect relation of it; he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willing to ſatisfie their curioſity, and not doubting that the more it was noiſed in the Court, the more deteſtable it <note n="*" place="margin">Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the Rebels.</note> would (by detecting <hi>Don Allonſoes)</hi> make him in the eye of all, was well pleaſed to give them this ſatisfaction, which done, he proteſted it would have drawn tears from any honeſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> mans eyes, to conſider in the earneſtneſs of this Prince, and theſe Lords, what influence his Majeſties Royal beams had wrought upon the hearts of ſtrangers abroad, whilſt our frantick Sectaries depriv'd us of that felicity at home, having expended his juſt purſuance of what they all concluded to be ſo important to the King of <hi>England,</hi> they offered him all the aſsiſtance that in them lay; and notwithſtanding that <hi>Don Allonſo's</hi> Greatnes was conſiderable enough to ſuch, as were leſs then himſelf, to be ſparing of too much freedom in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119316:8"/>
delivering their ſence againſt him; yet the ſtrength of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie's intereſt did ſo overſway that retentiveneſs which humane policy might have furniſh't leſs noble ſouls with, that they frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enveigh'd againſt the vileneſs of his proceeding therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>White,</hi> after he had delivered his letters from the Embaſſador, and ſeconded them with all poſſible importunity in the behalf of <hi>Scot,</hi> retir'd with as little ſatisfactionas (in the judgement of thoſe who ſtood at a diſtance) Spaniſh ſhougs &amp; frowns could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford him. Cap <hi>Comb</hi> giving way to tvvo or three more to take their audience, (of purpoſe to give his Excellency time to cool) approached once more, telling him that he doubted not but he vvould think this obligation a very vvorthy one, to be added to the number of thoſe his Maſter had already to his Catholique Majeſty, to his Excellency, and the State of that Countrey; and therefore having already the honor of a favorable audience, he came now to kiſs his hands, &amp; receive the confirmation of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor; the Marqueſs anſvver'd, that he vvas ſorry that in a matter of that nature vvhich himſelf vvas ſenſible vvas of conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the King of Great Britain; it did not ſo directly depend upon him, as he thought both himſelf &amp; others would judge, the whole affairs of England being by the Counſel referr'd to <hi>Don Allonſo.</hi> Mr. <hi>Comb</hi> reply'd, We are all the more unfortunate, &amp; his Majeſty the more diſ-obliged. <hi>Is there any one</hi> (ſaid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs) <hi>hath an ill ſence of</hi> Don Allonſo? To which was returnd, <hi>I have not (moſt Excellent Lord) what ſence the Court of Spain hath of him, neither am I of ſufficiency to be his accuſer; but from any that relate to his Majeſty of England, I never heard any words but what ſavoured of the greateſt diſtaſt, it he moſt notorious diſſervice to their Maſter, could animate them with all againſt him; &amp; therefore your Excellency (under correction) cannot employ your Authority more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>then by interpoſing it for the rectification of other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters errors, to prevent a miſ-underſtanding, which might unhappily produce inconveniences.</hi> There is (ſaid the Marqueſs) but one thing to be done of two, either to deliver him into the King's hand, or to baniſh him the countrey; the firſt I know not vvhether vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my ovvn Maſters command I may dare to do, to vvhich Cap. <hi>Combs</hi> a little haſtily anſvver'd, <hi>Oh Sir, be onely pleaſed to have him penned till the King be inform'd thereof, and I dare engage that his Majeſty will never expect his delivery upon any terms that may bring prejudice to you.</hi> Whereupon the Marq. laying his hand upon his,
<pb facs="tcp:119316:9"/>
aſſur'd him he vvould do vvhat lay in him, and that he vvould that night ſend about it. This being all he vvas able to obtain, he haſtned back to <hi>Bruxells,</hi> where having reported the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe's promiſe to the <hi>Aman,</hi> he conjured him to ſuffer the guards yet four and twenty hours, aſſuring him that, in that time there would be ſome order iſſued out: the <hi>Aman</hi> embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him in his arms, moſt curteouſly anſwered, Sir you would pity the clamors that I have endured ſince upon the retarding of this mans liberty, you went to Trereure; but to ſhew you how I value his Majeſtie of great <hi>Britains</hi> ſatisfaction above my own repoſe, I aſſure you that for twice 24 hours they ſhall not be diſturbed; but then when it appears that I have done more then I well could, you will pardon me if I excuſe my ſelf from attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting my abſolute ruine. M. <hi>Combe</hi> with very many thanks ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the aſſiſtance he really had found from him, took his leave. This is all he is able upon oath to averre, it being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to him whether the Marqueſſe perform'd his promiſe or not, or if he did, whether <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> ſmothered it ſo as the <hi>Aman</hi> could have no news thereof: However the <hi>Aman</hi> pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually perform'd his, inſomuch as for 2 days and 2 nights lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>Scot</hi> to his no little aſtoniſhment ſtill remained under cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody; but the third night at or about eleven of the clock the guards were removed, and he guarded (as it was certified to Captain <hi>Combe)</hi> by one of the town Officers at that time of the night out of the gates towards the principallity of <hi>Liege;</hi> this laſt is onely his preſumption drawn from the report of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but whether he were only removed to another lodging, or upon an eſcape to another Country, by the help of the convoy given him by <hi>Don Alonſo,</hi> imports not much, ſince nothing is more certain, then that in all this time <hi>Scot</hi> had never either ſpoken to, or ſo much as ſeen Sir. <hi>Harry Deuick</hi> (his Majeſties Agent there) and it is in no wiſe to be thought that ſuch a cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of running, riding negotiating, and threatning, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be imploy'd for the liberty of a man who had a mind to render himſelf: Captain <hi>Combe</hi> hereupon had no other courſe left unattempted, but to publiſh in every place as well in <hi>Don Alonſo</hi>'s houſe as elſe where, his intention to come and inform his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of the outrage done him; which to effect he with all ſpeed prepared for his journy, and ere he arrived at <hi>London, Scot</hi> was delivered up to the ſaid Sir <hi>Harry Deuich</hi> (his Majeſties Agent) and ſo ſent over, therefore not ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf according to Proclamation,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant C. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119316:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
